[SPEAKER_00]: Is love the path to happiness?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is love the path to happiness?
[SPEAKER_00]: Loving your family, loving your dogs, loving...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just nature, the nature of love in general.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does that bring happiness?
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: At the end of the day?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the short answer is absolutely not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the common phenomenon of love, it's inseparable from attachment.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're not attached to something, you're not loving it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the whole notion of, you know, the unconditional love, well, it's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're either unconditionally bound with it, or you're emotionally divorced from it, which means you don't love it, which means you're not attached to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in itself, love is a bond.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even you can make it as abstract and divine as you want, it's still a bond, because it still has its object, which means there is still some sort of attachment, to a degree.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, actually, like, that's just people's fantasy, very often, when they talk about the unconditional love and, like, an ideal, an abstract ideal, that, in practice, love is, it's, it's even worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's, it's, it's always, in fact, it's always mixed with infatuation, with lust, with delight, with conceit, with pride, with everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's, basically, what love is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Passion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Passion, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inseparable from passion.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's where you can kill, at the same time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fall forward.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can kill for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I'm sure that people who try to justify the love, they would think that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, trying to be unconditioned, have unconditioned love for everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that is just an ideal, basically, that you can't... that's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you're
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, love, be it even unconditional, is a relationship.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you are relating yourself to these things, which means to that extent you're bound by them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's impossible to have unconditional love.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's unconditioned, means there is no condition, there is no relationship.
[SPEAKER_01]: But love is a relationship.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's basically saying like, oh, eh... the unconditional conditioning, or the unconditionally conditioned, that's what unconditional love would be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or have a relationship with no relationship.
[SPEAKER_01]: That just... that's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can find that poetic value in saying contradictory terms, but in itself, in practice and phenomenologically speaking, makes absolutely no sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're either bound or you're free from the bound... from the... from the bond.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is love virtuous?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it a virtue?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it depends, but no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, love can be wholesome,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's one sort of slow in answering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Love can be wholesome in a sense of... it's not necessarily, you know, infatuated with passion and lust and greed involved with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as a bond, as something that is fundamentally still rooted in a degree of passion and emotion, it is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: From the point of view of enlightenment, it is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's an obstacle, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a bond that you need to break.
[SPEAKER_01]: Love or hate, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you want to be free from suffering, or if you want to develop your mind to the... well, it's full potential, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Potential freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Both must be abandoned equally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Both love and hate.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, love cannot bring happiness?
[SPEAKER_01]: It can bring worldly happiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which, from the ultimate point of view, it's not happiness, obviously.